Guide to the Records of the Steinhardt School of Education, Department of Occupational Therapy. 1941-1990 RG 26.25
New York University Archives
Records of the Department of Occupational Therapy, Steinhardt School of Education
Bulk, 1951-1958
1941-1990
RG 26.25
New York University Archives
3.0 linear feet (6 boxes)
In the 1940s the Department of Occupational Therapy at NYU was one of the first university-level institutions to educate occupational therapists. A key aspect of the program was the completion of research projects related to practice specialization. Student notebooks from 1951-1958 prepared during the practical training at hospitals in the tri-state area comprise the bulk of the collection. Department newsletters, a 1988 yearbook, and articles written by faculty members provide additional information about the department's history from 1941-1990.
Steinhardt School of Education. Department of Occupational Therapy.
Arrangement
Folders in the first five boxes are arranged alphabetically by author. Folders in Box 6 are arranged by topic.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Student Notebooks
Topical Files
Separated Material
Two films were removed to the Audiovisual Collection. Photos were removed to the Behlen and Labowitz portrait files and the University Archives Photo Collection.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of notebooks prepared by students for various classes taught at the Department of Occupational Therapy from 1951-1958. Frieda Behlen taught some of the classes, and some of the notebooks contain her comments. The collection also contains OT newsletters from 1947-1959 and 1989-1990, as well as a 1988 yearbook, a list of OT reference books, and faculty articles.
The collection has been divided into two series.
Series I: Student Notebooks, includes notebooks of Margaret Deutsch, Karen L. Faberman, and Lorraine Williams.
Series II: Topical Files, contains notes by Betsy J. Prince, OT newsletters from 1947-1959 and 1989-1990, a 1988 yearbook, a list of OT reference books, and faculty articles.
History of the Department of Occupational Therapy
In 1940 NYU's School of Education established a Department of Occupational Therapy (OT), making NYU one of a handful of universities to educate occupational therapists. From 1941 to 1942 Susan Colson Wilson, Director of OT at Brooklyn State Hospital, taught the first OT courses.
In 1942 Frieda J. Behlen became the first full-time instructor of the Department of Occupational Therapy. During those first years of the program's existence Behlen was in charge of program development as well as teaching all of the applied OT theory courses. In 1943 the program earned formal approval from the Council on Medical Education of the American Medical Association. NYU's was the only OT school at the time to offer courses for both day and evening students and to accept male students and African-American students.
In 1953 NYU's Department of Occupational Therapy developed a post-professional master's degree program, and in 1973, it established the world's first doctor of philosophy program in occupational therapy. In 1981 the Department developed innovative work-study post-professional master's programs that attracted students from around the world. A key aspect of these programs was the completion of master's research projects related to practice specialization.
The Department began to phase out the bachelor's degree program in 1993, requiring that all professional level preparation be done at the master's degree level. By focusing only on master's and doctoral students, the Department has reaffirmed its primary mission of innovative, quality professional education.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
Provenance
These materials were transferred to the University Archives from the Department of Occupational Therapy in 2005.
Behlen, Frieda; New York University.; Prince, Betsy J.; Steinhardt School of Education. Department of Occupational Therapy.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Newsletters.; Notebooks; Occupational therapy.
- Series I: Student Notebooks
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: photocopy of entire notebook., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: topical outline of a course and lectures., ca. Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: outside reading assignments., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: book reports., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: oral report., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: field trips., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. A notebook for Theory of Occupational Therapy 131.701: pamphlets., Sep 1951-Feb 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Deutsch, Margaret, photocopy of folders 9-12., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Contagious and Communicable Diseases/Industrial medicine/The Eye and Ear: Blindness and Deafness, 131.703, 131.714, May 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Medical and Surgical Conditions in a General Hospital/OT in General Hospitals, 131.703, 131.714., Apr 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. OT in General and Special Hospitals/Outline of Willard and Spackman Chap. 7, 131.701, Nov 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Disorders and Diseases of the Cardio-Vascular and Respiratory Systems/OT for Cardio-Vascular and Respiratory Disorders, 131.703, 131.714, May 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: photocopy of entire notebook., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: Innervation of the Lower Extremity., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: Innervation of the Upper Extremity., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: Cord., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: Brain., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Deutsch, Margaret. Survey, Analysis, and treatment of Neurological Conditions in OT, 131.715: A Syllabus of Cerebral Palsy Treatment Techniques., Sep 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: photocopy of entire notebook., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: General., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Thigh., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Thigh., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Thigh., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Leg., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Knee., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Leg., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Foot., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Foot., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Foot., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Shoulder Girdle., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Shoulder Girdle., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Arm., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Neck and Shoulder., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Arm., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Forearm., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Elbow., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Forearm., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: The Hand., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Hand., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Fingers., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Muscles of the Thumb., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Affections of the Hand., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Activities for the Hand., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Deutsch, Margaret.131.704, 131.705: Bibliography., Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Note from Frieda Behlen., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Photocopy of entire notebook., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Observation of the Patient., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Functional Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Psychosomatic Case Studies., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Metabolic Disturbances., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Heart, Rheumatic Fever, Rheumatic Heart., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Heart, Rheumatic Fever, Rheumatic Heart., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Diseases of Circulatory System., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Neoplasms., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Gastro-Intestinal Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Urinary Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Endocrine Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Respiratory Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Contagious and Communicable Diseases., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Visual Deficiencies., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Faberman, Karen L. Survey, Analysis, and Treatment of Medical and Surgical Conditions in OT, 131.714: Auditory Disorders., ca.1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: photocopy of entire notebook., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: ROM Testing., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: Muscle Testing., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: Splint Making., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: Bunnel Splints., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: Special Equipment., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: ADL Equipment., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Faberman, Karen L. OT Practicum, 131.725: Prosthetic Devices., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Textiles and Weaving, 031.734: Photocopy of entire notebook., Jan 1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Textiles and Weaving, 031.734: original., Jan 1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Photocopy of entire notebook., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Table of Contents., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Connecticut State Hospital/General Info., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Psychiatry/General Info., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Connecticut State Hospital/OT., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Attended Sessions & Lecture Notes., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Library Readings., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Art and Ceramics., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Scribe Notebook., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Men's OT Shop., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Industrial Placement Notebook., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Practice in OT, 131.706: Leak Hall Notebook., Jun 1956-Sep 1956 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Williams, Lorraine. OT Minor Crafts, 031.735: Photocopy of entire notebook., Jan 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Williams, Lorraine. OT Minor Crafts, 031.735: Original., Jan 1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Photocopy of entire notebook., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Orientation., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Glossary/Rehab. Info., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Special Sessions., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Case Studies., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Progress Notes and Sample Records., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Homemaking., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Homemaking Materials., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Woodruff Hospital Notebook: Rehabilitation Materials., Jun 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Affiliation/Bellevue Hospital Children's Recreation Service: Photocopy of entire notebook., Aug 1958 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Clinical Affiliation/Bellevue Hospital Children's Recreation Service: Original., Aug 1958 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Textile Construction. 031.736: Photocopy of entire notebook., undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Textile Construction. 031.736: Original 1 of 2., undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Williams, Lorraine. Textile Construction. 031.736: Original 2 of 2., undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series II: Topical Files
  - Prince, Betsy J. Collection from Various Publications of Adaptive Equipment for the Exercise and Use of the Upper Extremities. 131.704: Photocopy of entire work., undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Prince, Betsy J. Collection from Various Publications of Adaptive Equipment for the Exercise and Use of the Upper Extremities. 131.704: Original., undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Prince, Betsy J. Graded Activities for Use in the Home and Shop for the Limitation of Joint Motion. 131.704., Dec 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - OT Newsletters: Photocopies., Oct 1947-Mar 1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - OT Newsletters: Originals., Oct 1947-May 1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - OT Newsletters: Originals., Apr 1951-Mar 1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Willis, Barbara. "Iceland Comes to Port Chester" published in Dialogue., 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Zimmerman, Muriel E. "Homemaking Training Units for Rehabilitation Centers" presented as lecture at Univ. of Colorado., Jun 1965-Jun 1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Ayers, A. Jean. "The Effect of Sensory Integrative Therapy on Learning Disabled Children.", Nov 1976 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - OT Yearbook., 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - List of Reference Books for OT Students., 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Frieda J. Behlen's letter to Mr. Franklin Stein., Apr 1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Stein, Franklin. Activity Analysis of Unstructured Drama as Therapy. 131.702., Apr 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - NYU Progress Notes: Department of OT., Apr 1989-Apr 1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - VHS Tapes 1 and 2 Fiftieth Anniversary of OT Dept., Apr 1989-Apr 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - VHS Tape: Frieda Behlen Tourist Journal, Circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - VHS Tape: Frieda Behlen, Ann Mosey, Debora Lebowitz, Mary Donohue Tourist Journal, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Insignia, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Pedretti's photos, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Booklet "Then 1917 and Now 1967" by the American Occupational Therapy Association (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Textbook and papers from Ceramics course taught by Ruth Canfield, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Loose Papers, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Unlabled Folder, Papers from a Course on O.T., Notes by Frieda Behlen, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - O.T. Club Newspapers - Memoirs, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 10)